

Computer Science Building, Office 254, 140 Governors Drive, Amherst, MA 01003, USA

■ matteo@cs.umass.edu | 🎢 people.cs.umass.edu/matteo | 🛅 MatteoBrucato

## Summary.

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst. Advisor: Prof Peter J. Haas. Co-advisors: Prof Alexandra Meliou and Prof Azza Abouzied (NYU).

Ph.D. thesis on systems for scalable and easy prescriptive analytics. Thesis title: "Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data".

More than 8 years of experience in research, with several publications in top-tier conferences and journals in data and information management (SIGMOD, VLDB, CACM, VLDBJ). Multidisciplinary research, with publications in NLP, IR and robotics/Al conferences. Work recognized by several ACM awards (CACM, SIGMOD Highlights, invited VLDBJ, best demos and best paper at VLDB, best young research nominee in RANLP), and several scholarships (Krithi Ramamritham Computer Science Scholarship by UMass; merit, research and exchange scholarships by the University of Bologna).

More than 8 years of mentorship and advising experience. Mentored more than 20 students, at all levels (undergrad, master, and doctoral students), and managed several projects under my direct supervision.

Several industrial internships, both as researcher (MSR, IBM) and software developer (Cineca, Maggiore Hospital).

## Research Interests

Research areas: Data Management, Prescriptive Analytics, Decision Making, Stochastic Constrained Optimization, Fair Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Natural Language Processing, Information Retrieval.

Research interests: Theoretical and systemic aspects of constrained optimization, decision making and prescriptive analytics at a very large scale; Structured, unstructured, and natural query languages; Scalable and approximate algorithms; Systems for interactive data exploration; Scalable systems for fair ML; Scalable systems for AI and robotics; Personalized text summarization.

## **Education**

**UMASS AMHERST** Amherst, MA, USA

2013 - 2021

Bologna, Italy

2008 - 2011

Jan - Jun 2013

- Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE · Advisor: Peter J. Haas
- Co-advisors: Alexandra Meliou and Azza Abouzied (NYU)
- Thesis: Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data

#### UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA Bologna, Italy 2011 - 2013

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- · Summa cum laude
- Thesis Advisor: Danilo Montesi
- Thesis: Temporal Information Retrieval

## UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA

**B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE** 

- · Summa cum laude
- Thesis Advisor: Danilo Montesi
- Thesis: Mobile systems for patient-reported outcomes

## **EXCHANGE PROGRAMS**

· Advisor: Christian S. Jensen

#### **ÅRHUS UNIVERSITY** Århus, Denmark

EXCHANGE PROGRAM DURING M.S., COMPUTER SCIENCE

**UC RIVERSIDE** Riverside, CA, USA Sep - Jun 2011

EXCHANGE PROGRAM DURING B.S., COMPUTER SCIENCE

• Advisor: Vassilis J. Tsotras

## **Honors & Awards**

2020	Best demo award, VLDB 2020	Tokyo, Japan
2020	Best demo runner-up, VLDB 2020	Tokyo, Japan
2019	Krithi Ramamritham Computer Science Scholarship	Amherst, MA, USA
2018	CACM Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in CACM Research Highlights)	Amherst, MA, USA
2017	ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award (invited journal paper in SIGMOD Records)	Amherst, MA, USA
2017	Invited journal paper in the VLDB Journal, Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016	Amherst, MA, USA

MATTEO BRUCATO **DECEMBER 4, 2020** 

2016	Best papers, VLDB 2016	New Delhi, India
2013	M.S. with Honors, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2013	Best Young Researcher nominee, RANLP 2013	Hissar, Bulgaria
2013	Merit Scholarship, awarded to 0.2% of all students of the University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2012	Research Scholarship, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2012	Merit Certificate, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2012	Complimentary AAAI Membership, Stanford Online AI Course	Stanford, CA, USA
2011	<b>B.S. with Honors</b> , University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2011	Merit Certificate, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2010	Merit Certificate, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2010	Exchange Scholarship, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy

## **Publications**

- Samer B. Nashed, Justin Svegliato, M. Brucato, Connor Basich, Rod Grupen, Shlomo Zilberstein Solving Markov Decision Processes with Partial State Abstractions ICRA 2021 (under review)
- M. Brucato, Miro Mannino, Azza Abouzied, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou sPaQLTooLs: A Stochastic Package Query Interface for Scalable Constrained Optimization VLDB 2020
  - Rest Demo. Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1v5KevGKbfE
- Anna Fariha, M. Brucato, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou SuDocu: Summarizing Documents by Example VLDB 2020
  - Rest Demo Runner-Up. Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZGzF6cBSYjo
- 4. **M. Brucato**, N. Yadav, A. Abouzied, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou Stochastic Package Queries in Probabilistic Databases *SIGMOD 2020*
- 5. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou Scalable Computation of High-Order Optimization Queries
- Communications of the ACM (CACM) 2019
  6. **M. Brucato**, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

Package queries: Efficient and scalable computation of high-order constraints The VLDB Journal 2018 (Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016)

The VEDB 300 mar 2010 (Special issue on E

7. **M. Brucato**, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou A Scalable Execution Engine for Package Queries

SIGMOD Record 2017 (ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award 2017)

8. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, C. Blauvelt

Redistributing Funds across Charitable Crowdfunding Campaigns arXiv:1706.00070, 2017

9. **M. Brucato**, J. F. Beltran, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems *VLDB 2016* 

- Rest papers of VLDB 2016
- RInvited journal paper in the VLDB Journal (Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016)
- RACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in SIGMOD Records 2017)
- RCACM Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in CACM Research Highlight 2018)
- 10. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, and A. Meliou

Improving Package Recommendations through Query Relaxation VLDB 2014, at Data4U

11. M. Brucato, R. Ramakrishna, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

PackageBuilder: From Tuples to Packages *VLDB 2014* 

 K. Fernandes, M. Brucato, R. Ramakrishna, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou PackageBuilder: Querying for packages of Tuples SIGMOD 2014

13. M. Brucato, D. Montesi

Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval *ECIR 2014* 

- M. Brucato, L. Derczynski, H. Llorens, K. Bontcheva, C. S. Jensen Recognising and Interpreting Named Temporal Expressions RANLP 2013
  - 👭 Best Young Researcher award nominee

## **Professional Experience**

INDUSTRY

**Microsoft Research** Redmond, WA, USA

RESEARCH INTERN May - Aug 2017

Worked under the supervision of Kaushik Chakrabarti on natural language to SQL using neural networks.

**IBM Watson** 

T. J. Watson Research Center, Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

RESEARCH INTERN, WATSON HEALTH

Worked under the supervision of Shilpa Mahatma and Yajuan Wang on "conceptual queries" for healthcare applications.

CINECA Casalecchio di Reno, Bologna, Italy SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN Jun - Oct 2012

- Responsible for developing and managing a data warehouse and analytics system for a nationwide videoconferencing system.
- Duties included generating aggregated data and analytics, deployed through usable interfaces to let decision makers understand usage and performance of the videoconferencing system.

**Maggiore Hospital** Bologna, Italy

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (VOLUNTEER)

2011 - 2013

Jun - Aug 2016

- · Co-developed software to help the Emergency Room visit their patients using portable ultrasound technology.
- Software deployed on medical tablets to help doctors collect patient's information on the field.
- The collected data was then used to make better informed decisions in the Emergency Room.

### ACADEMIA

# DREAM Lab (Data systems Research for Exploration, Analytics, and Modeling), University of Massachusetts Amherst, MA, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Working with Prof Peter J. Haas, Prof Alexandra Meliou, and Prof Azza Abouzied (NYU Abu Dhabi) to create 🕎 Package Builder, a system that extends query engines to support the generation of packages, i.e., collections of tuples with global properties that are true of the entire collection.
- Technical paper at SIGMOD 2020
- Demo papers at VLDB 2020
- Invited journal paper at CACM Research Highlights 2019.
- Invited journal paper at the VLDB Journal 2018.
- Invited journal paper at SIGMOD Records 2017.
- Technical paper at VLDB 2016; workshop paper and demo paper at VLDB 2014; undergraduate research poster at SIGMOD 2014.
- Project website: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu.
- DREAM Lab website: dbgroup.cs.umass.edu.
- Project code: Scalable-PaQL-Queries on GitHub

## Design Technology Lab, NYU Abu Dhabi

Abu Dhabi, UAE

VISITING PH.D. CANDIDATE

Mar - May 2016

• Paper: Redistributing Funds across Charitable Crowdfunding Campaigns (arXiv:1706.00070).

AMPLab, UC Berkelev Berkeley, CA, USA

VISITING PH.D. STUDENT

May - Aug 2015

· Worked on extensions to Package Builder to identify ideal packages by example, under NYU Summer internship.

### Data-Intensive Systems Lab, Arhus University

Århus, Denmark

VISITING M.S. STUDENT

Jan - Jun 2013

- Worked on M.S. thesis on Temporal Information Retrieval under the supervision of Prof Christian S. Jensen.
- Actively collaborated with researchers within the group.
- Published two papers in main international conferences in the fields of NLP and IR.

## **Database Lab, UC Riverside**

Riverside, CA, USA Jan - Jun 2013

Undergraduate Research Intern (volunteer)

- Worked closely with a Ph.D. candidate and **Prof Vassilis J. Tsotras** on query optimization techniques for query result diversification.
- Developed a query parser for a SQL-like diversification query language.
- Devised and developed a query optimizer to select optimal diversification query plans.
- Developed client/server technology to issue and evaluate diversification queries.

## Advising & Mentoring

## Research Advisor for undergraduate student Agam Sandhu

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

2020

Agam Sandhu is working on scalable stochastic constrained optimization under costly sampling methods.

## Research Advisor for PhD student Ahmad Chatha (NYU)

Amherst, MA

Ahmad Chatha is working on combining scalable constrained optimization methods with scenario-based methods for stochastic optimization.

MATTEO BRUCATO **DECEMBER 4, 2020** 3 **Project Mentor (in collaboration with Microsoft)** 

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

Mentored MS students (Abdul Hannan Kanji, Parul Gupta, Ge Gao, Xinlu Liu) for their Independent Class project (CS 696DS), in collaboration with

Microsoft, to improve the Fairlearn library (https://fairlearn.github.io).

Research Advisor for MS student Kanchi Masalia

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

2020

 $Kanchi\ Masalia\ is\ working\ on\ SuDocu,\ a\ new\ system\ for\ personalized\ efficient\ document\ summarization\ by\ example.\ SuDocu\ website:$ 

http://sudocu.cs.umass.edu.

Research Advisor for undergrad Genglin Liu

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

Genglin Liu worked on the frontend of SuDocu, a new system for personalized efficient document summarization by example. SuDocu website:

http://sudocu.cs.umass.edu.

**Research Mentor for undergraduate student Kyaw Htet** 

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

**UMASS AMHERST** 

Fall 2019

Kyaw worked on analyzing scenario reductions methods for stochastic optimization.

**Project Mentor (in collaboration with Microsoft)** 

Amherst, MA Spring 2019

Mentored a group of four MS students (Katie House, Shanu Vashishtha, Deeksha Razdan, Cheng-Yin Eng) for their Independent Class project (CS 696DS), in collaboration with Microsoft to produce notebooks that showcase their Machine-as-a-service platform Azure ML.

Research Mentor for undergraduate student Nishad Ranade

Amherst, MA

**UMASS AMHERST** 

2018-2019

Nishad worked on Monte Carlo scenario reductions methods.

Research Mentor for 1st-year PhD student Nishant Yadav

Amherst, MA

2018

Nishant and I worked together on stochastic package queries.

Research Mentor for graduate student Sandhya Sankaranarayanan

Amherst, MA

Fall 2015

UMASS AMHERST

Sandhya and I worked together on extending the package query language PaQL.

Amherst, MA

Research Mentor for undergraduate student Kevin Fernandez

UMASS AMHERST

Spring 2014

Kevin and I worked together on evaluation techniques for package queries. This work was invited to present at the ACM SIGMOD 2014 Undergraduate Research Poster Competition.

Research Mentor for graduate student Rahul Ramakrishna

Amherst, MA 2013 - 2014

**UMASS AMHERST** 

Rahul and I worked together on interface abstractions for package queries. Our work was demonstrated at VLDB 2014.

**Teaching** 

**UMASS AMHERST** 

Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Database Systems (CS 345)

Amherst, MA

Fall 2020

Office hours, question answering, grading and labs.

Teaching Assistant for Undegraduate Class "A Networked World" (INFO 203)

Amherst, MA

UMass Amherst Homework grading.

**UMASS AMHERST** 

Spring 2018

**Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Introduction To Computation (CS 250)** 

Amherst, MA Fall 2017

Responsible for discussion sessions, occasional lectures, office hours, homework and discussion grading.

**Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Database Systems (CS 345)** 

Amherst, MA

**UMASS AMHERST** 

Fall 2015

Responsible for occasional lectures, project advising, office hours, homework and project grading.

**Professional Service & Leadership** 

**Reviewer**• IEEE Transactions of Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE).

**Guest Editorial Board** 

2014 - 2015

4

• Information Processing and Management, special issue on Time and Information Retrieval, Elsevier, 2014/2015.

DECEMBER 4, 2020 MATTEO BRUCATO

**External Review Committee** 2013 - 2015

- VLDB 2017
- SIGMOD 2015
- VLDB 2015
- RANLP 2013

**Lab Seminar Organizer** Amherst, MA, USA

UMASS AMHERST DATABASE LAB

2014 - 2015

• Coordinated weekly discussion seminar, including invited talks and paper readings, for the UMass Amherst Database Research group (~10 Ph.D. students and faculty), and webmaster duties.

**Student Seminar Leader** Amherst, MA, USA

UMASS AMHERST DATABASE LAB

Fall 2015

• Organized and coordinated a weekly discussion seminar among Ph.D. and M.S. students in the UMass Amherst Database Research group to foster research collaborations, exchange of ideas, group discussions, and group cohesion.

**Talks** 

INDUSTRY

Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems

Redmond, WA, USA

MICROSOFT RESEARCH

**Conceptual Queries for Multiple Data Sources** 

Austin, TX, USA

IBM Watson

Aug 2016

**Package Queries: From Tuples to Packages** 

Berkeley, CA, USA

BERKELEY LABS ACADEMIA

Jul 2015

Stochastic Package Queries For In-database Optimization Under Uncertainty

Virtually at INFORMS 2020

November 2020

sPaQLTooLs: A Stochastic Package Query Interface for Scalable Constrained Optimization

Tokyo, Japan (virtually) September 2020

VLDB 2020

Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1v5KevGKbfE

Portland, OR, USA (virtually)

June 2020

**Stochastic Package Queries in Probabilistic Databases** 

SIGMOD 2020

• Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UrEOEplK06I Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data

MIT CSAIL, DATA SYSTEMS GROUP

Cambridge, MA, USA Feb 2020

Stochastic Package Queries for In-Database Constrained Optimization Under Uncertainty MIT, NORTH EAST DATABASE DAY, SAMBERG CONFERENCE CENTER

Cambridge, MA, USA

Jan 2020

Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems

New Delhi. India

VLDB 2016

ECIR 2014

Sep 2016

• Slides: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu/papers/scalable-paql-presentation-share.pdf

**Package Queries: From Tuples to Packages** 

Berkeley, CA, USA

AMPLAB, UC BERKELEY

Jun 2015

Improving Package Recommendations through Query Relaxation

Hangzhou, China Sep 2014

• Slides: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu/papers/package-recomm-slides-web.pdf

**Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval** 

Amsterdam, the Netherlands

Apr 2014 Bologna, Italy

**Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval** 

Dec 2013

University of Bologna **Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval** 

Århus, Denmark

ÅRHUS UNIVERSITY

Jan 2013

MATTEO BRUCATO **DECEMBER 4, 2020** 5